Restaurants and the food industry in general
المطاعم وصناعة الأغذية في العموم
are pretty much the most wasteful industry
هي أكثر الصناعات إهداراً
in the world.
في العالم.
For every calorie of food that we consume here in Britain today,
فكل كالوري نستهلكه من الطعام في بريطانيا اليوم،
10 calories are taken to produce it.
يتطلب 10 كالوري لأنتاجه.
That's a lot.
وهذا كثير.
I want to take something rather humble
أريد أن أخذ شيئا إلي حد ما بسيط ومفيد
to discuss.
لإناقشه.
I found this in the farmers' market today,
وجدت هذا في سوق المزارعين اليوم.
and if anybody wants to take it home and mash it later, you're very welcome to.
لو أن أحداً يريد أخذها للمنزل وهرسها لاحقاً، فعلي الرحب والسعة.
The humble potato --
البطاطس المتواضعة.
and I've spent a long time, 25 years, preparing these.
لقد أمضيت مدة طويلة -- 25 سنة -- أعد هذا.
And it pretty much goes through
ولحد كيبر تمر خلال
eight different forms in its lifetime.
ثمانية أشكال في عمرها.
First of all, it's planted, and that takes energy.
أولاها، تزرع، وهذا يتطلب طاقة.
It grows and is nurtured.
تنمو وترعي.
It's then harvested.
ثم تحصد.
It's then distributed,
ثم يتم توزيعها،
and distribution is a massive issue.
والتوزيع موضوع كبير.
It's then sold and bought,
ثم تباع وتشترى،
and it's then delivered to me.
ثم تسلم إلي.
I basically take it, prepare it,
أنا بشكل أساسي أخذها، أعدها،
and then people consume it -- hopefully they enjoy it.
ثم يستهلكها الناس -- اّمل أن يستمتعوا بها.
The last stage is basically waste,
أخر مرحلة هي المخلفات.
and this is is pretty much where everybody disregards it.
وهذا إلي حد كبير ما يتجاهله كل الناس.
There are different types of waste.
هناك عدة أنواع من الإهدار.
There's a waste of time; there's a waste of space; there's a waste of energy;
هناك إهدار للوقت، هناك إهدار للمساحة، هناك إهدار للطاقة،
and there's a waste of waste.
وهناك إهدار للمخلفات.
And every business I've been working on
وكل الأعمال التجارية التي عملت بها
over the past five years,
علي مدار الخمس سنوات الماضية،
I'm trying to lower each one of these elements.
أنا أحاول خفض كل عنصر من هذه العناصر.
Okay, so you ask what a sustainable restaurant looks like.
حسناً، أنتم تسألون كيف يبدو المطعم الصديق للبيئة.
Basically a restaurant just like any other.
بشكل اساسي مطعم مثل أي مطعم.
This is the restaurant, Acorn House.
هذا هو المطعم، "أكورن هاوس"
Front and back.
المدخل والخلف.
So let me run you through a few ideas.
لذا دعوني أعرض عليكم بعض الأفكار.
Floor: sustainable, recyclable.
الأرضية: صديقة للبيئة، وممكن إعادة تدويرها.
Chairs: recycled and recyclable.
الكراسي: ناتجة من إعادة تدوير وممكن إعادة تدويرها.
Tables: Forestry Commission.
المناضد: لجنة الغابات.
This is Norwegian Forestry Commission wood.
هذا خشب من لجنة الغابات النرويجية.
This bench, although it was uncomfortable for my mom --
هذا المقعد، علي الرغم من أنه غير مريح لأمي --
she didn't like sitting on it,
لم يعجبها الجلوس عليه،
so she went and bought these cushions for me from a local jumble sale --
وذهبت وإشترت هذه الوسادات من سوق الأشياء المستعملة --
reusing, a job that was pretty good.
أعادة الإستخدام، كانت فكرة جميلة جداً.
I hate waste, especially walls.
أكره الإهدار، خاصة الجدران.
If they're not working, put a shelf on it, which I did,
إذا لم تكن مخصصة لعمل، ضع رفاً عليها، وهذا ما فعلته.
and that shows all the customers my products.
وهذا يعرض منتجاتي لكل العملاء.
The whole business is run on sustainable energy.
المطعم بالكامل يعمل بطاقة صديقة للبيئة.
This is powered by wind. All of the lights are daylight bulbs.
هذا يدار بطاقة الرياح. كل الإنارة هي من ضوء النهار.
Paint is all low-volume chemical,
الطلاء من نوع ذو كيماويات منخفضة،
which is very important when you're working in the room all the time.
وهذا شي مهم جداً عندما تعمل في الحجرة طول الوقت.
I was experimenting with these -- I don't know if you can see it --
كنت أجرب هذا -- لا أدري إذا كنتم تستطيعون رؤيتها --
but there's a work surface there.
لكن هناك سطح للعمل.
And that's a plastic polymer.
و هذا بوليمر البلاستيك.
And I was thinking, well I'm trying to think nature, nature, nature.
و كنت افكر، حسنا كنت احاول التفكير في الطبيعة، الطبيعة، الطبيعة.
But I thought, no, no, experiment with resins,
لكني فكرت، لا، لا، جرب الراتنجات،
experiment with polymers.
جرب البوليمرات.
Will they outlive me? They probably might.
هل ستعمر أكثر مني؟ في الأغلب نعم.
Right, here's a reconditioned coffee machine.
حسناً، هذه ألة صنع قهوة مجددة.
It actually looks better than a brand new one -- so looking good there.
في الحقيقة أنها تبدو افضل من الجديدة -- تبدو جميلة هناك.
Now reusing is vital.
الأن إعادة الإستخدام شيء حيوي.
And we filter our own water.
و نحن ننقي مياهنا.
We put them in bottles, refrigerate them,
نضعها في زجاجات، نبردها،
and then we reuse that bottle again and again and again.
ثم نعيد إستخدام الزجاجات مرات ومرات ومرات.
Here's a great little example.
هذا مثال صغير رائع.
If you can see this orange tree, it's actually growing in a car tire,
إذا كنت تستطيعون رؤية شجرة البرتقال، أنها حقيقة مزروعة في إطار سيارة،
which has been turned inside out and sewn up.
تم قلبه وحياكته.
It's got my compost in it, which is growing an orange tree, which is great.
وبداخله السماد، الذي ينمي شجرة البرتقال، وهذا رائع.
This is the kitchen, which is in the same room.
وهذا هو المطبخ، وهو بنفس الحجرة.
I basically created a menu that allowed people
وبشكل أساسي أبتدعت قائمة طعام تسمح للناس
to choose the amount and volume of food
بإخيتار كمية وحجم الطعام
that they wanted to consume.
التي يريدون إستهلاكها.
Rather than me putting a dish down,
بدلاً من أن أضع أمامهم الطبق،
they were allowed to help themselves to as much or as little as they wanted.
فمسموح لهم بإختيار كمية التي يريدونها قليلة أو كبيرة.
Okay, it's a small kitchen. It's about five square meters.
حسناً، أنه مطبخ صغير. حوالي خمسة أمتار مربعة.
It serves 220 people a day.
يخدم حوالي 220 شخص في اليوم.
We generate quite a lot of waste.
نولد الكثير من المخلفات.
This is the waste room.
هذه هي غرفة المخلفات.
You can't get rid of waste.
لا يمكنك التخلص من المخلفات.
But this story's not about eliminating it, it's about minimizing it.
لكن هذه القصة ليست عن التخلص منها، أنها عن تقليلها.
In here, I have produce and boxes
هنا، لدي منتجات غذائية وصناديق
that are unavoidable.
وهذا لا يكمن تجنبه.
I put my food waste into this dehydrating, desiccating macerator --
أضع مخلفات الطعام في هذا المجفف،
turns food into an inner material,
الذي يحول الطعام إلي مادة داخلية،
which I can store and then compost later.
أستطيع تخزينها ثم أحولها لسماد في وقت لاحق.
I compost it in this garden.
أسمد بها هذه الحديقة.
All of the soil you can see there is basically my food,
كل التربة التي ترونها هناك هي في الأساس طعام،
which is generated by the restaurant,
تم توليدها من المطعم،
and it's growing in these tubs, which I made out of storm-felled trees
وتنمو داخل هذه الأحواض، التي صنعتها من الأشجار التي أقتلعتها العواصف
and wine casks and all kinds of things.
وبراميل النبيذ وأشياء أخري عديدة.
Three compost bins --
ثلاث صناديق من السماد --
go through about 70 kilos of raw vegetable waste a week --
تنتج من حوالي 70 كيلو من مخلفات الخضروات النيئة في الاسبوع --
really good, makes fantastic compost.
حقاً جيد، تصنع سماداً رائعاً.
A couple of wormeries in there too.
وهناك صندوقين لصنع السماد عن طريق الدود أيضاً.
And actually one of the wormeries
وحقيقة أحد هذه الصناديق
was a big wormery. I had a lot of worms in it.
كان كبيراً، وكان لدي الكثير من الدود به.
And I tried taking the dried food waste,
وحاولت أخذ مخلفات الطعام المجفف،
putting it to the worms, going, "There you go, dinner."
ووضعها للدود، قائلاً، "تفضلوا، العشاء."
It was like vegetable jerky,
كان مثل الخضروات المجففة،
and killed all of them.
وقتلهم كلهم.
I don't know how many worms [were] in there,
لا أعلم كم من الدود بالداخل،
but I've got some heavy karma coming, I tell you.
لكن أستطيع أن أقول لكم أني حسابي سيكون عسيراً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What you're seeing here is a water filtration system.
وما ترونه هنا هو نظام هو نظام تنقية للمياه.
This takes the water out of the restaurant,
يأخذ المياه الخارجة من المطعم،
runs it through these stone beds -- this is going to be mint in there --
ويمررها خلال الفرش الحجرية -- مما سيحسن حالته بالداخل --
and I sort of water the garden with it.
وأنا نوعاً ما أروي الحديقة بها.
And I ultimately want to recycle that, put it back into the loos,
وفي النهاية أريد أعادة تدوير ذلك، وأعادته لدورات المياه،
maybe wash hands with it, I don't know.
ربما لغسيل الأيدي به، لا أعلم.
So, water is a very important aspect.
لذا، المياه جانب مهم جداً.
I started meditating on that
بدأت التفكير في هذا
and created a restaurant called Waterhouse.
وأنشأت مطعم إسمه ووتر هاوس "بيت الماء".
If I could get Waterhouse to be a no-carbon restaurant
لو أستطعت جعل ووترهاوس مطعم خالي من الكربون
that is consuming no gas to start with, that would be great.
أي لا يستخدم الغاز أساساً، سيكون ذلك رائعاً.
I managed to do it.
أستطعت فعل ذلك.
This restaurant looks a little bit like Acorn House --
هذا المطعم يبدو مثل أكرون هاوس قليلاً --
same chairs, same tables.
نفس المقاعد، نفس المناضد.
They're all English and a little bit more sustainable.
كلها إنجليزية الطراز وصديقة للبيئة بشكل أفضل قليلاً.
But this is an electrical restaurant.
لكن هذا مطعم كهربائي.
The whole thing is electric, the restaurant and the kitchen.
كل شيء يدار بالكهرباء، المطعم و المطبخ.
And it's run on hydroelectricity,
ويدار بالطاقة الكهرومائية،
so I've gone from air to water.
إذن فقد إنتقلت من الهواء للمياه.
Now it's important to understand
الأن من المهم أن نفهم
that this room
أن هذه الغرفة
is cooled by water, heated by water,
يتم تبريدها بالماء، وتدفئتها بالماء،
filters its own water,
وتنقي مياها،
and it's powered by water.
وتدار بطاقة الماء.
It literally is Waterhouse.
أنها حرفياً منزل مائي.
The air handling system inside it --
نظام التهوية بها،
I got rid of air-conditioning
تخلصت من مكيف الهواء،
because I thought there was too much consumption going on there.
لأني أعتقدت أن هناك إستهلاك كثير.
This is basically air-handling.
هذا بصفة أساسية نظام للتحكم بالهواء.
I'm taking the temperature of the canal outside,
فأنا اخذ الحرارة من القناه بالخارج،
pumping it through the heat exchange mechanism,
أضخها عبر ألية التبادل الحراري،
it's turning through these amazing sails on the roof,
وتدور خلال هذه الأشرعة المذهلة الموجودة علي السطح،
and that, in turn, is falling softly onto the people in the restaurant,
وهذه بدورها تهوي بنعومة علي الناس بالمطعم،
cooling them, or heating them, as the need may be.
تلطفهم، أو تدفئهم، حسب الرغبة.
And this is an English willow air diffuser,
وهذا شجر الصفصاف الإنجليزي الموزع للهواء.
and that's softly moving
و هذا يحرك بنعومة
that air current through the room.
تيار الهواء عبر الغرفة.
Very advanced, no air-conditioning -- I love it.
متقدم للغاية، بدون مكيف للهواء -- أنا أحبه.
In the canal, which is just outside the restaurant,
في القناة، الملاصقة للمطعم،
there is hundreds of meters of coil piping.
هناك المئات من الأمتار من اللفائف الأنبوبية.
This takes the temperature of the canal
هذه تأخذ الحرارة من القناه
and turns it into this four-degrees of heat exchange.
وتحولها إلي نظام تبادل الحرارة ذو الأربعة درجات.
I have no idea how it works, but I paid a lot of money for it.
ليس عندي أدني فكرة عن طريقة عمله، لكني دفعت فيه مبلغاً كبيراً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what's great is one of the chefs who works in that restaurant
وما هو رائع أن أحد الطهاة الذين يعملون في المطعم
lives on this boat -- it's off-grid; it generates all its own power.
يعيش علي هذا القارب -- أنه يولد الطاقة الخاصة به --
He's growing all his own fruit, and that's fantastic.
أنه يزرع الفاكهة الخاصة به، وهذا رائع.
There's no accident in names of these restaurants.
أسماء هذه المطاعم لم تكن صدفة.
Acorn House is the element of wood; Waterhouse is the element of water;
أكورن هاوس هو عنصر الخشب، ووترهاوس هو عنصر الماء،
and I'm thinking, well, I'm going to be making
وأفكر، بل أني سأنفذ،
five restaurants based
خمس مطاعم مبنية
on the five Chinese medicine acupuncture specialities.
علي الأفرع الخمس لطب الأبر الصينية.
I've got water and wood. I'm just about to do fire.
لدي الماء والخشب. وأنا علي وشك البدء بالنار.
I've got metal and earth to come.
وسيأتي المعدن و الأرض لاحقاً.
So you've got to watch your space for that.
لذا يجب أن تراقب مساحتك لذلك.
Okay. So this is my next project.
حسناً، هذا هو مشروعي التالي.
Five weeks old,
عمره خمسة أسابيع،
it's my baby, and it's hurting real bad.
هو وليدي، وهو مؤثر بشدة.
The People's Supermarket.
سوبرماركت الناس.
So basically, the restaurants only really hit
إذن بصورة أساسية، المطاعم فقط تؤثر
people who believed in what I was doing anyway.
بالناس الذين يؤمنون بالفعل بما أفعل.
What I needed to do was get food out
ما أردت فعله هو إخراج الطعام
to a broader spectrum of people.
إلي مدي أوسع من الناس.
So people -- i.e., perhaps, more working-class --
إذن الناس -- ربما الطبقة العاملة --
or perhaps people who actually believe in a cooperative.
أو الناس الذين يؤمنون بالتعاونيات.
This is a social enterprise,
أنها مؤسسة إجتماعية،
not-for-profit cooperative supermarket.
سوبرماركت لا يهدف للربح.
It really is about the social disconnect
أنه عبارة عن الفصل الأجتماعي
between food, communities
بين الطعام، المجتمعات
in urban settings
في المناطق الحضرية
and their relationship to rural growers --
وعلاقتها بالمزارعين في الريف --
connecting communities in London to rural growers.
نربط المجتمعات في لندن بالمزراعين في الريف.
Really important.
فعلاً مهم.
So I'm committing to potatoes; I'm committing to milk;
لذا أنا أدعم البطاطس، أدعم اللبن،
I'm committing to leeks and broccoli -- all very important stuff.
أدعم القرنبيط -- كلها أشياء مهمة.
I've kept the tiles; I've kept the floors;
أحتفظت بالبلاط، أحتفظت بالأرضيات،
I've kept the trunking; I've got in some recycled fridges;
أحتفظت بالتمديدات، لدي ثلاجات معاد تدويرها،
I've got some recycled tills; I've got some recycled trolleys.
لدي ماكينات بيع معاد تدويرها، لدي بعض العربات المعاد تدويرها.
I mean, the whole thing is is super-sustainable.
أعني، كل شيء صديق للبيئة بشكل كبير.
In fact, I'm trying and I'm going to make this
في الحقيقة، أنا احاول وسوف أجعل هذا
the most sustainable supermarket in the world.
أكثر سوبرماركت صديق للبيئة في العالم.
That's zero food waste.
هذا يعني عدم وجود إهدار للطعام نهائياً.
And no one's doing that just yet.
و لا أحد يفعل ذلك حتي الأن.
In fact, Sainsbury's, if you're watching,
في الحقيقة، سينسبري، لو أنكم تشاهدون،
let's have a go. Try it on.
جربوا.
I'm going to get there before you.
سأصل لذلك قبلكم.
So nature doesn't create waste
إذن الطبيعة لا تنتج مخلفات
doesn't create waste as such.
لا تنتج مخلفات تحديداً.
Everything in nature is used up in a closed continuous cycle
كل شيء في الطبيعة يستهلك في دورة مغلقة مستمرة
with waste being the end of the beginning,
والمخلفات هي نهاية البداية.
and that's been something that's been nurturing me for some time,
وهذا شيء كان يراودني منذ فترة.
and it's an important statement to understand.
وهي عبارة مهمة يجب أن نفهمها.
If we don't stand up
إذا لم نقف
and make a difference
ونحدث فرقاً
and think about sustainable food,
ونفكر في طعام صديق للبيئة،
think about the sustainable nature of it,
ونفكر في طبيعته الصديقة للبيئة،
then we may fail.
فمن الممكن أن نفشل.
But, I wanted to get up and show you
لكن -- أردت أن أريكم
that we can do it if we're more responsible.
أننا نستطيع ان نفعل ذلك لو كنا أكثر مسئولية.
Environmentally conscious businesses are doable.
الشركات الصديقة للبيئة شيء من الممكن تحقيقه.
They're here. You can see I've done three so far;
أنها هنا. يمكنكم أن تروا أنني نفذت ثلاثة حتي الأن:
I've got a few more to go.
ولدي البعض الأخر للتنفيذ.
The idea is embryonic.
هذه الفكرة في مرحلة أولية.
I think it's important.
أعتقد أنها مهمة.
I think that if we reduce, reuse, refuse
أعتقد أننا لو أستطعنا تقليل، أعادة إستخدام، الإحتفاظ بالمخلفات
and recycle -- right at the end there --
وإعادة تدوير -- هي في النهاية تماماً.
recycling is the last point I want to make;
إعادة التدوير هي اخر نقطة أعرضها.
but it's the four R's, rather than the three R's --
ولكنها أربعة طرق وليست ثلاثة.
then I think we're going to be on our way.
حينها أعتقد أننا سنكون في طريقنا.
So these three are not perfect -- they're ideas.
إذن هؤلاء الثلاثة ليسوا كاملين -- أنهم أفكار.
I think that there are many problems to come,
أعتقد أنها هناك كثير من المشاكل ستأتي،
but with help, I'm sure I'm going to find solutions.
لكن مع المساعدة، أنا متأكد أني سأجد حلول.
And I hope you all take part.
واّمل أنكم ستشاركون.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرأ جزيلاً.